Good afternoon and welcome to the public
services committee meeting on September
8th. Is that right? [laughter]
Um on a Tuesday instead of a Monday due
to the holiday. Um please turn your uh
cell phones to manners mode if you're
here in the chambers with us. And if you
are going to join us and would like to
make comments virtually, please make
sure you use use make use of the virtual
hand and then Jennifer will arrange for
you to be able to speak. We will be
using a threeminut timer today. And so
with that, if we can have the first
item, please.
Number seven, resolution naming a
triangle-shaped parcel of real property
located at the intersection of Randall
Avenue and Kribbon Avenue as the Robert
M. Far Park
>> and staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, Jason Sanchez, Community
Recreation and Events. Um before you
today for consideration is a petition
that we received from um some of Dr. as
far as neighbors and friends that wish
to name a parcel of property located on
Cribbon and Randall. It's about 210 of
an acre. Um in honor of Dr. Far for his
many contributions he's made to the
community. Um the folks that have made
this recommendation have met all the
city requirements. We have over 414
signatures on their petition. um they
are here today and they would like to
speak and give uh you also a little
handout on some of the accomplishments
that Dr. Far has had in this community.
Um in regard to the city and for the
city I would say that uh Dr. Farre
maintained the parcel that is um being
described today for more than 20 years.
Uh before we had irrigation systems and
mowing he was watering it and mowing it
taking care of the area and so we we
support this uh request and I would
stand by for questions.
>> Thank you.
So at this point we will do you have any
questions for staff? Go ahead gra you
chairman.
>> I just um I spoke with uh director
Sanchez briefly coming in the room. I
remember about five years ago we created
a criteria for uh naming of public
facilities. I just want to make sure
that we've we've reviewed that. I
believe you have uh at one point I
thought there was a 5-year waiting
period but apparently not for this type
of parcel. Is that correct sir?
>> Madam Chair you that is correct. We I do
have a copy of that. It was approved in
April of 2021 and as I stated um I I
believe they've met all the criteria
that the city has set forth for this.
>> Thank you.
Any other questions for staff?
Okay. Hearing none uh we will go out for
public comment. So welcome
If you'll state your name for the
record, please.
>> I'm Martha Mullikin and I live at the
corner of Persing and Cribbon next door
to Bob Farre and right across the street
from the triangle that we are
discussing.
>> Thank you.
The neighbors of Bob Far have submitted
a request for the naming of the Triangle
Park on the corner of Randall and
Kribbon in his honor. We are here to
discuss our reasons for wanting to
recognize Bob Thor.
the development and expansion of Randall
Avenue, including the connection to the
military base in the early 19 early 90
1900s with several small unused triangle
parks parcels throughout the area
because this is an entrance into
Cheyenne.
Many of those
uh se areas have been transformed into
small parks for the enjoyment of the
residents and visitors alike. These are
mixed in with our houses and very
important to us. For the past 46 years,
Bob Far has lived on the Duboce block
and the William Duboce home. During this
time, he has become a dedicated steward
of the triangle at Randall and and
Cribin. Throughout the early years, he
was instrumental in keeping the area
watered and clean for the enjoyment of
the neighborhood adults and children.
Um
over the years, children, families, and
adults have enjoyed this the small park
as a place for recreation and
gatherings.
One of the the cheerleader groups has
used it as their place to go practice. I
think it's maybe Central or McCormick
and the cheerleaders would come down and
do their practicing there. and it was
was real fun to see them out our
windows. Bob Bob's efforts have helped
preserve it as a welcoming community
space and an important part of the
neighborhood during CFD.
Uh, a lot of people park their
cars there and then they picnic in that
area waiting to go up to the uh, rodeo
grounds because it is a short walk,
eight blocks up to the rodeo grounds and
it's well used during frontier days. Bob
has always demonstrated a deep sense of
pride and affection for his local
community. He is always he was always
first to welcome new neighbors and share
the history of the area with them. At
one time the our block was on the
historic well we went through the
procedure to get it on the historic
register and the whole block now is on a
his on the historic register.
>> Thank you for your time. Your time is
up.
>> All right. Thank you.
I've
have these to pass out to you.
[laughter]
It's an additional amount of
organizations that Bob has been partial.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> Part of Thank you.
>> Is there anyone else who would like to
make public comment?
>> We have someone online. Jennifer
Nate K, you can unmute yourself.
>> Hello. Can you hear me? Okay.
Yes, we can.
>> Okay. Thank you for your time,
everybody. My name is Nate Katherine.
I'm with Go Rail. You're gonna um
>> I think Nate, you're wait you're wanting
to make comments on the next item.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Okay. We're going to put you on hold for
just a minute while we finish up this
one.
Any other public comment regarding um
item number seven, naming a
triangle-shaped parcel of real property
um for Robert Mfar?
Any public comment online?
Hearing none or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam chair, I would move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Crave
and a second from Councilman Leborn. Um,
is there any discussion?
All in favor? Oh, go ahead. Sorry.
[clears throat]
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. This is u
certainly a case of someone who has made
that contribution for many years and has
uh done a lot for that neighborhood. I
hope that
all right [clears throat]
I think that there's other cases uh of
triangular parks uh that probably would
benefit from something like this if
that's the case. I know that our water
bug program's been gone for quite a
while, but those uh triangular areas
aren't. So, uh I speak in favor of this
uh designation and make the point that
we need to uh be communicating with
neighbors. Uh maybe there are some
others that have that same kind of
community feeling. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman Lebornne. Any
other comments?
Okay. Um all in favor say I. I
>> opposed.
This item will move forward with
recommendation to adopt. Um, next item,
please. Number eight, resolution
opposing federal legislation or
regulations that increase maximum truck
size or weight limits on national
highways.
And
can I turn it over to you, Councilman
CRA, while I do the staff report?
>> Absolutely.
>> Um,
>> staff report.
>> Thank you. Um so uh Dr. Michald County
City Council Ward 3. Uh this is a
resolution that came about um after
meeting with the coalition against big
trucks and also the go rail um in
representatives. This is a um there is a
bill working its way through Congress
right now that would increase the
vehicle weight limit from 80,000 lbs to
91,000 lbs going through our community
as they make deliveries and as they are
transporting goods. Um it also um has
[clears throat] a lot of um implications
when we look at our weather as well as
how our roads are developed and what
they're built for. So, at this point, I
would like to ask um engineer Cobb to
address the um weight amount that our
roads are typically built for uh
throughout our community.
>> Director Cairman
Secret um to Dr. Dr. Aldridge. Dr.
Aldridge. So, we look at these things as
equivalent single axle loads. So, we
take whatever load it is and equate it
to basically a 20,000 lb load for
equivalent single axle loads. So, I
can't tell you specifically on every
single street off the top of my head.
Um, but we look at a 20-year design life
for whatever structure we're looking at,
whether it's residential,
collector, or arterial. And I can get
you some more information. I was
unprepared to answer this question for
you today, but I'm happy to furnish that
information to you if you give me some
time.
>> Thank you. Thank you, sir.
>> Anything further?
>> The only other thing that I would like
to add is that this is uh the uh Senate
bill that is being proposed is coming
from large distributors such as Amazon
uh who are hoping to get more load per
more weight per load um in order to
lower their trucking cost. And so that
that's what the impetus is at the
federal level.
>> Any questions from committee for staff?
Dr. Emmens.
>> Um thank you, Mr. Chairman. I have a
question for um Councilwoman Aldrich.
Does this also the the bill that they're
looking at also include triple trailers?
>> It does.
>> And so would this limit that?
>> Well, right now, um in Wyoming, we don't
allow triple trailers. Um, so that would
require legislative change at the state
level as well, but at the federal level,
that's part of this proposition. And I
believe that uh Nate Kaplan is going to
make public comment and can address that
as well. Thank you.
>> Further questions for staff.
Hearing none, we'll open it to the
public and I'll give it back to Dr.
Aldridge.
>> Thank you, Councilman Crave. Um, so we
will um go ahead and open up for public
comment. And so I believe we have Nate
Kaplan.
You can go ahead Nate.
>> Thank you everybody. Good afternoon
council members. Um thank you for taking
on this issue and addressing
the situation u facing increasing truck
size and weight on our interstate
freeways and state and local roads. Uh
the current weight limit on interstate
freeways is 80,000 lbs. Um according to
US DO 80,000 pounds um uh the amount
taxes and and diesel tax that these um
trucking companies pay and shippers pay
cover about 80% of the cost of the
damage um that is uh on our bridges and
uh freeways and roadways. Um so that
means anyone else who pays a gas tax, we
subsidize the 80,000lb truck limit um by
20%. Now, if that goes up 91,000 pounds,
which these shippers, as Dr. Alish
mentioned, are looking for um that would
exponentially increase the amount of
impact and damage um caused by each axle
and which would entail that everybody
else um who pays into the federal
highway trust fund um would be
subsidized and continue to subsidize and
increase costs of trucking on our public
roads. Uh so usually um this is an issue
that comes up every year or two. Um it's
comes in the the form of a 10y year
pilot program which is um kind of hard
to fathom because usually after 10 years
um pilots turn permanent unless there's
something really drastic that happens.
So, it's a very much a slippery slope.
And, uh, my understanding is that on an
interstate freeway, um, if this does
pass that an interstate freeway through
Wyoming or any state that bans triple
trails would have to accommodate those
on the interstate freeways since those
are federal highways. Um, that is my
understanding. Um, so we are very much
um, tense in posting where trucks are a
very important part of the the railroad
um, network. um first mile, last mile,
as well as um longer shipping halls, um
trucks and and and trains work together
closely on making sure all our goods get
to where they need to go safely and
efficiently. And um this is an issue
that is opposed by sheriffs, um police
chief associations, um trucking
association. The American Trucking
Association is against the increased
weight as well as the team stirs because
it puts their drivers at a much greater
risk of injury or accident. Um, as Dr.
Aldrich mentioned, this is usually going
to be pushed by large shippers i.e.
Amazon or UPS and uh we think that the
current weight limit right now is um
where um it is should be maintained.
So, uh, thank you for your time and
thank you for considering this item. And
if you have any other questions, I'm I'm
more than happy to to answer. Thank you.
Are there any other public comments?
Okay. Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> Chairman, I would move to adopt.
>> Second. We have a motion by Councilman
Crave and a second by Dr. Emmens to
adopt. Um, comments. Councilman Labour.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. I think this
is a a case of where uh corporate
America and the people or the businesses
that run it are taking advantage of us
and are really um causing uh if this was
to pass, a long-term problem not only in
Cheyenne, but the state of Wyoming, the
interstates that we use. And uh I think
when we look at that, we can all uh do
what I did this weekend, which is drive
down the interstate and see all the ads
for
uh attorneys who specialize in uh truck
accidents.
Uh that didn't used to be the case and
it's something that uh obviously is very
serious to the highway users. I
personally believe that probably
uh those corporations are benefiting
from the existing situation and we
should definitely be passing this along
to our congressional delegation
as our concern for our roads and the
public safety out on the uh interstate
and the other highways in Wyoming. As we
all know, we're having some real trouble
here funding and maintaining our uh
transportation system. So, this would
just add more uh to that problem. So, I
speak very much in favor of this. Thank
you.
>> Any other comments?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to adopt at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 9 C right-of-way use
agreement between the city of Cheyenne
and CSRE properties Wyoming LLC for two
connections of storm storm sewer pipe
from detention ponds in the Ventura
Drive right away staff report please
>> good good afternoon Dr. Aldrich um
chairman and members of the public
service committee um Tom Cobb um city
engineer before you and for your
consideration obviously is a right of
use agreement between CSRE Properties
Inc. and the city of Cheyenne. The
primary purpose of the rideway use
agreement is to allow them to place um
two pipes into the rightway of Ventura
Drive um from their new newly
constructed detention ponds. The purpose
of the agreement really is to define the
responsibilities and the expectations on
both parts and primarily I'll give you
the two two components that I feel are
the most important which is going to be
it's going to be on page two of the
agreement. It's two 3D and F. And the
first one is if the city should ever
have for any reason construct,
reconstruct, move or abandon any portion
of the city's road within the facility,
utility or device located, the lenses
shall be required as requested by the
city to move without delay and for the
city's benefit. So that's the first most
primary most important and secondly it
defines that all maintenance
responsibilities is on the individual
property owner. Um and with that I'll
take any questions you might have. Thank
you. Any questions from committee for
staff?
Okay. Hearing none, we'll go out for
public comment. Any public comment.
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none, I
would entertain a motion.
Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion from Dr. Emmens
and a second by Councilman Crave. Um,
any discussion?
All in favor say I. opposed.
Okay, this item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please.
>> Number 12G, ordinance, second reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land west of Roundtop Road and
adjacent to HappyJack Road.
>> Okay. Staff report
chair and members.
Okay. uh chair, members of the
committee, Connor White, Planning and
Development Department.
So, this was uh the taxation. It was
postponed on second reading. Um
I'll go back through just a little bit
on the background. I know there was a um
council work session that was held on
this as well.
So, with the annexation um the
annexation is for
two different properties technically.
Um, with the annexation, you do have the
Cox Ranch property, uh, as well as some
city- owned land. With this, uh, it's
for the water treatment plant.
The, uh, annexation is for roughly
1,259.91
acres in total.
Um
with this sanexation uh it is contiguous
to city limits.
There is water and uh water in
HappyJack. Sewer is adjacent to
HappyJack does not extend all the way uh
down HappyJack but can be extended
um with annexation. Uh basically when a
property is annexed like this and
developed they will have to hook to city
water and sewer. So that does uh prevent
them from being able to do well and
septic uh which I know is a concern of
um nearby residents is that will this be
on well and septic? Are they going to be
drilling into the aquifer? If it is
annexed into the city and developed it
will not. Uh they are required to hook
to city water and sewer.
Uh fire protection would be extended out
to this area is already in the area. Um
the North Range Business Park is under
city jurisdiction. So we do a fire
service that already extends out this
direction. Same with police services.
So that's just kind of some background
on it. Again, this annexation um it's
two different properties that are in
there. The reason that the city land is
part of the annexation is when this was
submitted, uh, Board of Public Utilities
has been wanting to annex the city land
um, that's out there, which we can do
separately, but because an annexation
that was adjacent was uh, basically
being proposed, we asked if we could
basically add that in there. Um, the
water treatment facility is not
affiliated with the development of the
Cox Land at all. is just city- owned
land that uh board of public utilities
would like to annex into city limits.
There are other items on the agenda for
this. There is the assigned zoning and
the zone change and then the future land
use map amendment uh is not on this
agenda. It was postponed
to the next public service committee uh
because the final reading of the future
land use map amendment needs to happen
at final reading of all the other items
with the uh assigned zoning that will
include both properties. The zone change
only includes Cox Ranch. The zone change
does not include the city-owned
property. I know I'm jumping ahead a
little bit, but I just want to make that
distinction clear that um
the lands are kind of separated as they
go through uh this process.
Again, with annexation, um annexation is
basically determining if it develops in
the city or the county. Uh it does not
define the use that is allowed on the
property at this time. That's we'll
discuss basically that when we get into
the zoning.
With that, I am available for any
questions.
>> Great. Thank you. Are there any
questions for staff? Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. Chairwoman, um,
who initiated the annexation,
>> Madam Chair, through you. Uh, the
annexation was initiated by
Cox William S. Res uh, Rev Revocable
Trust um, initiated the annexation,
which is the land owner for the
larger thousand acre parcel.
Um, Madam Chair, so just to be clear,
this was not a city requested
annexation.
>> Madam Chair, through you. That is
correct.
>> Thank you,
>> Councilman Crave.
>> Madam Chair, through you.
[clears throat]
Connor, could you go through the
benefits of uh developing in the city
the health, safety, welfare,
um all of the all of the uh requirements
for
um annexation according to state
statute.
>> Thank you.
manure through you. So with the first
criteria um which deals with the health,
safety, welfare uh basically this
annexation improves the health, safety,
welfare um by bringing it under city
building, fire and life safety codes
which uh provide more consistent
protection than unincorporated
standards. It allows uh for coordinated
police and fire response and a larger
response improving emergency services
and coverage for future development in
the area. Uh access to city water and
sewer instead of relying on private
wells and septic systems. Reduces
long-term groundwater impacts that could
affect downgradient properties. And city
zoning allows for the uh city to
regulate land use intensity, noise,
light pollution, which helps improve uh
help helps protect surrounding rural
residents uh residential areas and
ensures more uh compatible development
patterns over time.
uh with number two which is the urban
development and the area sought to be
annexed as uh constitutes a natural ge
uh geographical economic social part of
the annexing city or town.
Um this area is a peninsula directly
connecting uh connected to the city via
state highway corridor which provides a
functional and geographic link. The
highway corridor supports local
development patterns and effect uh
efficient extension of infrastructure
and services
um
with city zoning and utilities. Future
development will occur in a coordinated
manner with water and sewer services
instead of uh dispersed well and septic
systems.
Again, city zoning also enables
regulations of noise and light impacts
and then over time the area will
naturally orient towards uh Cheyenne for
services, employment and commerce and
become a part of the social and economic
fabric.
Um number three is the logical feasible
addition.
Uh
it's a logical extension of the city due
to the direct adjacency and access to
the state highway corridor. Police and
fire services can be extended
immediately upon annexation and again
they're already in the area.
Uh water and sewer services can be
feasibly feasibly uh extended based on
the proximity to extending
infrastructure. Uh again water is
already in HappyJack and extends the
entire length of the property along
HappyJack. sewer would have to be
slightly extended but is possible.
Um
again the city zoning authority ensures
orderly predictable development that
supports efficient infrastructure
planning and land use compatibility
annexation allow and then again some of
these kind of overlap on each one. Uh
but the city does regulate noise and
light impacts and then providing water
and sewer services avoids the reliance
on wells and septic systems.
Uh number four is just about the
contiguity. It is uh 5.26%
contiguous.
Um
number five is about franchise utilities
which are in place
uh for electricity and fiber and
basically any of those utilities. And
then number six is about the mailing um
which again a certified mailing was sent
out on March 13th of 2026 to all proper
um basically land owners incorporated in
the annexation and property owners
within 300 ft
and those were delivered
u around March 16th or
yeah were delivered around March 16th.
Um the public hearing was April 13th and
20 business days prior to April 13th was
March 16th. So we did meet the criteria
for mailing as well um being within that
20 days.
>> Madam Chair, follow up.
>> Sure.
>> Connor, if if this property were to
develop residential in the county
on a thousand plus acres, theoretically
you could get I don't know 150 200 homes
in that area. Is that reasonable?
um shared through you I would say so if
you're looking at if they're doing 10
acre
>> lots then yeah you could probably get a
100 out there which they could go down
as low as 5 acre lots so you can make
that a lot more which would then all be
on well and septic so those those would
be developed on well and septic so
regardless of how this property is
eventually developed um for the health
safety and welfare of the neighborhood
developing on the water and sewer system
of the city versus potentially 100 to
150 200 maybe wells and septic systems.
Is is that is that our reasoning there
m3? Yes, that would be that I believe
would fall under the h health safety and
welfare is if this was to develop in the
county they would be on well and septic
regardless of the development even if it
developed as a data center in the county
which is still possible even if it's not
annexed.
>> Right. Thank you very much. Thank you.
Any other questions?
Okay, hearing none. Um, we'll go ahead
and go out for public comment. Is there
anyone here in the chambers that would
like to make public comment?
>> Mr. White.
>> Uh, through you, Madam Chairman. Michael
White. Um,
I'd like to make the opportunity to
thank uh, Gay Woodhouse on working out
one of the issues that we had originally
with this property, but I'd like to
mention a couple things. U, I'm a member
of what's called the Wyoming Farm
Bureau. Um, not too long ago,
Governor Gordon had a meeting with the
U.
regulatory agent of commodity activities
and addressing annexation with regard to
not being allowed to talk about what the
future development of this project is.
The state of Texas decided to
put a moratorum on this and I'm not
going to mention the part that I'm not
allowed to speak about, but Governor
Gordon instructed his staff to get
recommendations that he has not been
informed with to basically get a handle
on these annexations with regards to
what's going to be there.
I appreciate Skybox and everybody else
that testified at the committee of the
whole to give us some more information,
but I believe at this time we are still
at the point to where we need to put a
hold on this.
Another point I'd like to mention is
making sure I say that with respect to
Councilman Edmonds. She made the point
on who made the recommendation.
The last time I was here, I made the
recommendation that the people from
Skybox be uh AVI can do that part, but
where are the people from the city? Me,
this still needs to be a separate issue.
City property, city property is owned by
the city. So, us piggybacking this on
again to me is not following the rules.
In addition to that, we have a land
owner that's west of this project and
during the committee the whole we still
don't know the results of what that
gentleman feels about this. So at this
point I still believe that we don't have
enough concrete information for the
public to continue with this. So I would
recommend on behalf of only myself that
we still put a pause on this and if not
vote no. Thank you.
>> Thank you Mr. White. Thank you for um
keeping your comments germaine to the
topic of annexation. So we'll move
forward. Thank you.
>> Thank you members of the committee. Tom
Glissmy Bios Group partners with Skybox
Data Centers. You could think of us as
co-developers who build, lease and
operate data centers. Um, we have a few
slides that if I could uh go through
>> and is is this Tom is this uh gerine to
the annexation for the zoning?
>> It it is uh project as a whole project.
So, if if if there's a if there's a a
different or better time to go through
these slides, then I'm happy to do that.
>> Uh what would be the pleasure of the
committee? I believe it would be more of
a zoning
>> concern. So, I'd like to wait till we
take comments on zoning.
>> Okay, great. I'll I'll just maybe
make notice that we are planning a
September 15th openhouse event open to
the public. That will be our fifth event
over the last two months. So, uh 12:30
p.m. at the library.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon, Madame Chairwoman, Dr.
Aldrich, members of the uh committee. My
name is Cindy Dansancy. I'm here on
behalf of uh Via West Skybox. Um
Germaine to the annexation. We
respectfully request that the annexation
be granted. We also have a short video
related to some of the issues that um
planning staff outline related to water
usage that I think would be helpful for
the public as well as the committee um
to um see. And so hopefully we're able
to pull that uh that video up um yeah
>> I think the first few slides are related
to water, correct?
>> Uh it's a video. Yeah, it's just water
usage and
>> we did get a a slide deck copy.
>> The slide deck is the presentation that
Mr. Glymmer was going to talk the
committee through. So
Um, madame chair, committee members,
Brad Evans, AVI agent for the owner and
applicant on this project. Um just
wanted to uh go back through some of the
annexation criteria and the fact that we
have met with all the franchise
utilities, Black Hills, the fiber
companies, um BOU um early on in the
process uh also with white dot um making
sure that the future access points can
be accommodated along HappyJack Road. Um
so um and then a little bit more I guess
clarity on the BOU annexation when uh we
decided to move forward. I think Boou
just said there's surveyors out here in
the area and it's never going to be
easier to get the survey map and
everything put together. And so that's
when the the Board of Public Utilities
decided to join in on the annexation was
when they uh knew we were going to be
out there surveying and getting all the
information already. So um and I believe
Frank's here as well if there's more
questions on about the B the Boo portion
of the annexation.
Uh Dr. Aldidge,
>> what's there cost savings uh to the city
by doing this annexation? Backing the
city's annexation on to the annexation
that was already being proposed.
>> Chairman, you to councilman Aldridge,
there would be just in the the setup
time of the survey equipment and
everything else. um and just having it
all and less maps to produce. I mean,
those are very small, but probably the
largest portion would be um getting the
survey equipment set up and the people
out there in the field.
I think we'll turn it back to you, Dr.
>> Hi, Heather Madrid. I live in W one. I
am here to oppose this annexation. While
I do appreciate the efforts made by
these particular developers and their
attorney and their willingness to put
mitigation commitments in writing, they
have the misfortune of coming in behind
Meta Microsoft related digital related
digital and the rest of the countless
massive developments who've made no
effort whatsoever to truly be good
neighbors beyond words at the podium.
developers lean on annexation as a
necessary step in order to justify
proper studies. Um, and while that might
be true, I'll give him the benefit of
the doubt on that one. That does make
sense. The problem is that annexation,
amending what has become a built suit
land use map and reszoning to a business
park all happen within minutes. There is
no time to study or plan anything to
ensure adherence to their new proposed
zone. These measures need to be
consecutive, not concurrent. If all
annexations proposed in the month of
September September are approved, 40% of
Cheyenne will be a business park with
the trend being used by right
permitting. How can you ask us to pay
for upkeep of nearly half of Cheyenne
while we are intentionally left in the
dark about what goes on? How can you say
that this makes good sense and is
protecting the community when you are
rapidly expanding the physical area that
taxpayers are responsible for without
also growing the tax base in a
meaningful way? I understand that these
developments generate property tax
revenue, but that doesn't fund
everything and doesn't seem to even be
funding what it's supposed to. As we
watch so many neighborhood schools close
and are asked to vote to tax ourselves
more to remodel the jail and build new
fire stations, the benefits aren't
trickling down to the community in a
sustainable way. That is the point of
the community benefit agreement.
Community benefit agreements should be
negotiated with the community, not only
the government. It needs to go beyond
mitigation, which is baseline. It should
benefit everyone beyond the construction
phase. Please consider making changes on
your end in writing. Otherwise, any
agreement a developer
volunteers is simply that voluntary with
no guarantees that they won't back out
down the road when the people who made
the promises aren't around to keep them.
Um, I also think that
if we want this in the city only if it's
a data center and not if it's housing
developments, that kind of flies in the
face of the care about water argument.
Um, and I also disagree that these two
separate annexations are being
piggybacked. That's I mean that God
knows what that opens the door for us in
the future if we start doing that now.
Thank you. I believe we have a question
for you by Dr.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. Um, Miss
Madrid, I just want to be clear
um with the uh community benefit
agreement that you spoke of. If we had a
community benefit agreement in place,
you would be okay with this data center
and this annexation?
>> I would. I mean, no, but it would be
better than nothing. I I think it's
really unfortunate. I think these guys
of all the developers that have come
here have done the best job of trying to
involve the community and actually
take actionable steps like with the
mausoleum and with letting adjacent
property owners continue to graze their
animals. And I think it's unfortunate
that we have allowed
ourselves, well, I don't know if we've
allowed it, but we have been ran over by
so many different developments at this
point that I just don't think we have
room for more and more and more. But
yeah, a community benefit agreement
would have changed my mind a long time
ago, but I feel like that ship has
sailed, unfortunately.
um just for clarity, but that's not
going to if we had one that's not going
to make you okay with the concept. Is
that correct?
>> If community benefit agreements were
negotiated with the community,
not with the council or with Cheyenne
leads. I mean, not only with you guys.
We need to have a seat at the table. We
don't right now. We just we don't. These
open houses aren't enough.
Um, I think again this these guys
excluded. They've done a good job, but
they're one of I can't even count, you
know, but we need to be included and
that would change a lot of things. I
think that, and I'm not trying to speak
for everybody, but I know that I'm not
alone in saying that involving the
community in these agreements
would greatly diminish the opposition.
like these there probably wouldn't be
any more seven-hour meetings.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Good afternoon. Who's chairman? Mr.
Chairman,
>> Madam Chairman,
>> uh Dr. Aldridge Gay Woodhouse. I'm an
attorney here in Cheyenne. I work with
Woodhouse, Roden, Ames, and Brennan. I'm
of councel with that firm and as such I
have been uh hired to represent Cox
Ranches LLC which is Beverly Cox Black
and her brother Mark T. Cox IV. Um, I
explained a little bit earlier at the
work session about how we got here and
uh the this land was given to Bill Cox,
a younger brother of my two clients uh
when he lived with his mother uh Betty
Cox under I believe some pressure, but
she did it and it included the
mausoleum. So the mausoleum we uh or
they understood would be kept taken care
of because it was William Cox his his
resting place. He's in the mausoleum
along with Betty Cox and Mark T. Cox III
and some other relatives. So
they were blindsided when they realized
that this entire parcel was included in
the proposed annexation
and so were the people who intend to buy
this uh parcel, the ones we've been
talking about um Bowest and Skybox. But
immediately they started they started
talking to us the same night they found
out and we were able to work through all
of our issues in terms of the
preservation of that mausoleum the the
land around it access to it. They were
very sensitive about it. They were
caring. They were understanding. We had
meetings face to face with them
listening to what my clients had to say
about what their concerns were and
ultimately have signed an agreement that
they are very happy with that will
preserve that mausoleum in perpetuity.
So I cannot say enough about how much
they did. I appreciate it and I have to
also acknowledge that if this annexation
doesn't go through it it probably won't
happen.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment in
the room?
>> Mr. Eley, thank you for being here.
>> Madam Chairman, uh, grateful to have the
opportunity to speak. Mark Eisley, King
Ranch owner and operator, uh, south of
the proposed annexation. I am really
just here to say that we'd like, and
I'll jump ahead a little. the zoning.
We'd like to make sure that we stay in
agriculture. Uh we don't want to be
annexed into the city. We've had some
great discussions with your staff. Uh
AVI and Skybox Vest, they've been great.
Everyone has reached out to us and I
think we're in a position where we're
supportive of this. We really don't want
to see a subdivision come into this. Uh
the potential on the water use is death
to us and I think death to the rest of
that water table and that repairing area
that we're actually the headwaters of.
So that being the case at this point
we're very comfortable. Uh they have
reached out and all those uh hopefully
those boxes have been checked and the uh
eyes have been dotted and the tees have
been crossed. So at this point we are
comfortable with it.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment here
in the room?
>> Hearing none or seeing none we'll go to
online. I believe we have Chris.
>> Yes. Hi my name is Chris Galves. or two.
Um,
madam chairman through you. Uh, I wanted
to say I don't believe that the request
for annexation seems to meet the
contiguous requirements per the state
statute
the state statute. I think there are
some um some of the wording is for 75%
and so what I heard the the staff report
it's only 5.26% 26% of that total
perimeter is contiguous to city. And so
I think for that reason it it doesn't
make logical sense to to grant
annexation. Um I also do not support the
annexation based on the impact to the
watershed. Um that does not seem to have
been investigated clearly. Councilman
Labor and you I think you pointed out
the working session um that the the
impact of where this this building is
like proposed that it would go would sit
right in that drainage um and could
impact that water table. And so until
that's completely studied, I I could not
support this annexation. Um and I do
fully support uh the requirement of a
community benefits agreement to be in
place before any annexation. Um the the
statements that it's too premature to
put anything in place, I think is a
false narrative. We're able to know
based on prior projects what the
development will likely look like and
put in a good faith agreement prior to
those developments being put in place.
Um and anticipating the the question of
would I support it if a community
benefits agreement was in place. I think
it depends on what the conditions of
those agreements are and how the city
council is planning for the total
development of the city of all of the
different data center development and
taking that as a full picture not as a
project by project um lens. And then
lastly, the the idea that we are lumping
together the water reclamation land
annexation and this annexation does not
seem like it I don't know when that got
lumped together. Like what process that
went through to com combine these two.
They're two different requesters and so
it seems like I don't understand how
that could even be possible. If somebody
could maybe answer that question.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any
other public comment online?
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second. Okay. Okay, [clears throat] we
have a motion by Councilman Crave and a
second by uh Dr. Emmens um to approve.
Is there any discussion?
>> Councilman Crrave
>> through you to uh Connor White, please.
Um the discussion from uh the last
speaker about uh 75% and and contiguous
I think those are two different issues.
Could you perhaps clarify that for us?
>> Yeah, madam madam chair through you uh
Conor White Planning and Development
Department. So in state statute, the 75%
that was referenced is if the city
initiates annexation.
So this goes back to our county pocket
discussion kind of. Um the city can
initiate basically forced annexation if
an area is 75% surrounded. We haven't
done that. We've only done 100. Uh but
that's where that requirement comes in.
Otherwise, when it comes to just owner
petitioned annexations, it just says it
needs to be contiguous.
Um,
so that that's what's in state statute
and I believe Mr. Lloyd might come and
correct me if I'm wrong or provide more
information.
>> Mr. Lloyd.
>> Madam Chair, if I may, Seth Lloyd with
the city of Shine Planning and
Development Department. Um, there are
four different ways to add land to the
city and state statute. One of them is
an addition by Platt. I have never done
that in my time here, so I don't exactly
know the process on that one very
clearly. Um, another is when the city
initiates an annexation of city- owned
land. Means the city is the sole owner,
city is the sole initiator. Um, that's a
different process. A third is when the
city initiates annexation of land it
does not own. Um, that's where the 75%
contiguous comes in. Um, the 75% is only
where um, people being annexed cannot
protest. So the city can actually
initiate an annexation where the land is
only say 10% contiguous. But at that
point if people pro enough people
protests that annexation be stopped. Um
and then the fourth is by landowner
petition. The landowner petition
annexation process only requires a
majority of the land owners to petition.
It does not require 100% of land owners.
And also that exempts any taxexempt
entity from that requirement. So, if
there was um a land owner who if there
were three land owners and they
requested to annex a church and uh two
other properties that didn't sign on,
the church as a taxexempt property would
not count against that majority and then
three owners versus two owners, the
three owners would be over the two
owners. So, um because this is a
landowner annexation and because the
city is taxexempt, um that can be added
without the city officially signing any
petition to annex. I hope that clarifies
all of those elements of statute and
annexations. There's certainly a lot
more I could delve into.
>> This is men chairman uh chairwoman
throughu. Could you explain the city's
land that we're the city is trying to
annex? Um I I always understood that
city- owned property regardless of where
whether it was contiguous or not could
be annexed. Uh why did why did the city
choose to go this route for this uh
additional I'm not sure the acreage um
small parcel
>> madam chair through you um it goes back
to uh a
what's the word efficiency um of
operation there's already going to be
surveyors out there's already going to
be maps being made the city staff was
informed the board of public utilities
would like that area to be annexed
anyway um we were aware the board of
utilities, public utilities wanted to
annex that prior to um this annexation
coming forward. So, we were going to go
under the process of the city doing
being the sole owner of land and having
a non-ontiguous annexation because we
can do that if we're the city sole
owner. However, because they were this
land owner was in the process became in
the process of doing annexation, we're
like, "Oh, that'll make everything
easier for us to annex that land as well
on the same time." And as we mentioned
with the landowner petition aspect, um
they can just add it as part of their
annexation without having to get our
signature or go through any form formal
process because we're a taxexempt
property at that location.
>> I think Mr. Strong may have something to
add behind you
>> through you. Um yeah, it we thought it
would be a convenience. We were getting
ready to start our own process to start
the annexation. this came in like, well,
it just makes sense to just sit through
one session at city council. I didn't
know they were going to be eight hours
or 10 hours, so I apologize for that. We
thought this would be just a simple way
for us to annex the water treatment
plant.
>> Thank you. Any other questions?
Councilman Cra. Hey,
any other discussion?
>> Councilman Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. I have a
number of questions and comments I'd
like to make here on the record.
>> Are they related to zoning? I mean to
annexation or to zoning.
>> They're related to the matter before us,
which is annexation.
>> Thank you.
>> Might be a little bit different than
what we do sometimes,
but I have some questions for the
representatives of Skybox and Via West.
Could they come and answer them?
Okay.
>> And the reason I ask these questions,
Madam Chairman, is I'd like to establish
uh the bonafides of these this business
and where they've have operated and what
they the circumstances around those uh
creations of those data centers. So, how
many data centers are you involved in?
This is this is um only about zoning or
I'm sorry only about annexation. So,
>> Madam Chairman,
>> are you ruling that the questions that
we might ask of this applicant as to
their business practices
are irrelevant to this discussion?
>> I'm ruling that those would be gerine to
the zoning conversation that we will
have on the next item.
Do you have any other items or questions
related to annexation?
>> Yes, I do.
>> Okay.
>> And they're very specifically related to
our work session here last Friday.
>> I would point out that uh
um the question of the mausoleum
really delayed uh this whole matter
until it could be resolved. So that was
a physical question on that property
that obviously was very unique
was uh a reason probably one of the main
reasons that uh this was delayed from
April I believe. So I think that that
the physical conditions on that site are
very relevant to the annexation
and I'd like to speak to that because I
couldn't
at the work session,
but I'd refer the members of the
committee and anyone else to the Skybox
and VS West project here uh on this uh
photograph here on the front page.
And on that photograph, you can see
uh the drainage that runs through that
property
from the treatment plant.
And I think that that is a physical
condition that is very relevant to this
annexation.
if the conditions
uh that are on the site and the uh
proposals that have been brought forward
raise questions along this line. I think
that's relevant to this discussion. Do
you agree, Madam Chairman?
>> If it refers to annexation, I would
agree. And I believe Mr. Strong is
waiting to answer your questions.
You're not really answering my question,
Madam Chairman. My question is, are
those physical conditions on that
property relevant to this discussion on
the record as to what conditions exist
out there and how they will affect the
development of that property and the
city of Cheyenne? Since this is uh as
we'll see here in a little bit very
directly related to the treatment plant
that is proposed for annexation as well.
So uh could you please tell me what I
what what I am allowed to speak to
today? Councilman Labborn, we will
address anything that is related to
annexation during this time and when we
go to the next item, then we will talk
about future development of this
property and the zone that is being
proposed for it.
Well, Madam Chairman, maybe I've made my
point here and I would like to uh have
Mr. Strong come up and tell us a little
bit about how the uh treatment plant
does operate and how that swale or
waterway um leaves our treatment plant
crosses this property and affects uh the
creek uh undoubtedly affects the uh
water table there. Um so might I ask Mr.
Strong some questions about that?
>> Yeah, Councilman Emmens. Madame Chair, I
my question would be the uh water center
water facility isn't going to change
processes whether it's annexed or not.
So I'm a little bit confused I guess as
to the direction of this.
>> May I answer madam chairman?
>> Yes.
>> Well that's exactly my point. Thank you.
The point is that the treatment plant
was constructed at that site. It's been
there for many years. And what it does
is it runs uh lake water and mixes it
with uh some of the uh well water that
we use and discharges from that plant uh
what I generally refer to as wash water.
Um and so it's a very significant amount
of water. uh and this discussion of uh
how we uh look at the water issues here
um has impact uh in discussions I've
heard the possibility of using that for
reinjjection
or some other purpose but uh Mr. Mr.
strong, could you tell us how much water
uh the plant releases uh on an average
basis or over time? I know it's not
every day, but I believe it's a very
significant amount of water. Is that
correct?
>> Uh through you, ma'am. Um I I believe
it's like like 150 acre feet a year. It
is not a significant flow compared to
the 14,000 acre feet we deliver to the
city of Cheyenne each year. And
regardless of whatever happens on this
property, whether it's residential,
business, data center, they're going to
have to design, you know, that storm
water channel to continue to function,
continue to allow water to flow through
their property. Um, what whatever goes
in there really won't impact our
operations because we can design around
it. They will have to design around with
it. They have to protect the wetlands
that are established or replace them.
They're going to have to continue to let
the water flow through the through the
property to the Crow Creek. So, the BOP
really doesn't have any concerns with
with this impacting our operations at
the water treatment plant.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Strong.
>> Okay. Well, that's um the Board of
Public Utilities opinion and I'm glad to
get it, but uh I think when we look at
this issue,
uh some of the comparisons that were
made earlier in this meeting really
become
questionable in my mind. I don't think
anyone is ever going to uh develop
residential property across the broad
wetland that is going to continue and
obviously this will continue and 5,000
acre feet uh is a very significant
amount of water and how it reaches
>> he said 150 acre feet.
>> Did you say 150 acre feet?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Gosh, I don't hear like I used to but
thank you Frank. uh that's uh even a
more significant uh amount of water
and I think that it's uh very important
that we consider this and
>> um council labor maybe I'm not clear 150
150 acre feet compared to the 14,000 we
delivered to the community
>> right well that's a um I don't know the
relevancy of the comparison to your
entire system but the point is it's it
is a significant amount of water. It is
released on a regular basis. It affects
that property and the wetland and it
certainly affects Crow Creek and the
recharge that we have here. So, that's a
that's an important part of uh the
discussion. I I
fail to understand how uh it could not
be a consideration and particularly
consideration that I think that the uh
property owners in the residential
subdivision uh that's not across the
fence but nearby might be quite
interested in and how it recharges
and what those effects are. So, um,
certainly I, uh, think I've made my
point here, Madame Chairman, but, uh,
before I leave, I would like to ask, uh,
Mr. Mr. Strong, if he's here, um, about
the, uh, possible sewer extension in
that area. I'm I'm aware that for years
we've talked about uh increasing that
sewer connection down Happy Jack and
into town and down Missile Drive and
where there's a variety of ways it can
go. But is uh
where when does the consideration come
into play that those um
expenses should be shared by the
developer? Are you considering that uh
perhaps some help would be in order for
that sewer line? Yes, madam through you
um with any development and I guess I
should start off uh Skybox Bow West
approached us numerous months ago about
this and you know we convey to them
immediately that all off-site
improvements are going to be at their
cost and this could include upsizing the
sewer main across the Little America
property. So our standard practice is
the developer pays for everything they
need to get to their development whether
it's on their site or offsite. We use
the the but for principle, but for you,
we wouldn't be doing this, so so we're
not paying for it.
>> Thank you. I think we're back to
annexation.
Did you have any other questions
regarding annexation alone, Councilman
Lelay?
>> Well, no. I I have a some comments about
the way that this committee meeting is
being run. I have some comments about
the way the uh work session was run.
>> Madam Chairman,
that's not relevant.
Thank you. Um, so we're going to go
ahead and we're going to
>> Madam Chairman,
>> yes, Councilman Lebornne,
>> my understanding and belief of this
matter
based on the information that's before
us is absolutely relevant. It might not
be shared,
but clearly there's a reason that I'm
here. There's a reason that the people
sent me, and there's a reason I can look
at and comment on procedure and process
at these meetings, which I find to be um
limiting in the sense that we have a lot
of meetings out in the community, but
this meeting is on the record,
>> right? And so in in light of that and um
in because you were sent here to uh do
the work of the people and to vote uh
we're going I'm going to go ahead and
call for the vote. So all in favor say
I.
>> I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council on second
reading. Next item please. Number 12H.
Ordinance, second reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, establishing the zoning
classification of AG agricultural and P
public for annex to the city of Cheyenne
located west of Round Top Road and
adjacent to Happy Habjack Road.
>> And staff report, please.
>> Madam Chair, Conor White Planning and
Development Department.
>> So the assigned zoning, it's like all of
our other assigned zonings. It's
basically what we give the land upon
annexation. Um, so this establishes what
uses are allowed on the land at that
time.
With the assigned zoning, staff reviews
it for what the current property is
being used as, adjacent properties,
existing zoning out in the area. So with
the assigned zoning, staff is
recommending that the Cox ranch land be
assigned to AG agricultural upon
annexation and then the city's parcel
would be zoned Public upon annexation.
Um this is all just based on existing
conditions with the Cox ranch land. It
is for the most part vacant is used as
ranching land. So upon annexation it
would be zoned AG. And then the
following item is the zone change which
is a own or applicant requested zone
change specifically to the Cox Ranch
land which would then establish the
zoning and uses allowed under that zone
district which we will discuss.
>> We will take that separately. Yes, that
will be at the that will be the next
item. So, this is just the assigned
zoning for the AG and the P public. Um,
I'll explain more with the zone change
kind of why even staff looks at all
these items individually. Um, but I can
go over that with the next item. So,
with this, it's just the assigned zoning
that comes after annexation to give it a
city zone uh upon annexation so that it
has a zone district should the zone
change not get approved.
>> Okay. So we are going to take public
comment on only the change to AG
agricultural which is likened to what it
is existing in the county and P for
public uh on the portion of the land
that's being annexed that belongs to the
city of Cheyenne.
>> Madam Chair, yes. May I ask Councilman?
>> Um I just want to clarify in the county
what is the current zoning?
>> Madam Chair, through you. Uh in the
county it is LU land use. Uh that zone
district
has a whole slew of different uses that
are allowed in that zone district. I
think by right it allows like single
family residential. Pretty much
everything else is a conditional use
including data centers, rock quaries,
larger multif family developments. All
of that is allowed in the LU. They just
have to go through some additional
processes.
>> Thank you. Okay. Any other questions for
staff? Okay. Public comments, Mr. White.
>> Uh through you, Madame Chairman. Michael
White. Um
I'd still like to make the point on um
I think we making a bad precedent on
taking city property
along with the property that we're
talking about
to put them together and do it in one.
I respect Mr. strong and the BOPU for
what they felt was their intent, but I
don't believe that meets the intent of
what this governing body needs to hang
their hat on. If you start doing that,
then we can come up here and do whatever
we need as a developer, as a person that
wants to develop property and just
piggyback everything and do it all at
once. So I object to the fact that we
are still at this point putting two
pieces of property into one for the sake
of I guess convenience and convenience
to me does not meet statute and does not
meet what the intent of what the
governing body should be doing. So I
believe at this time we should not do
that. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any other public
comment? We're talking about the zoning
to AG agricultural and P for public for
land.
Hi Heather Madre Ward one. Um I agree
with what was just said and I also think
that to limit what we're allowed to say
while allowing the developers and their
attorneys to show closed loop videos
pertaining to data centers is
like you can't have it both ways. That's
that's actually pretty bad. That's all I
have.
There any other public comment.
Is there any comment online?
Hearing none. Seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Chairwoman, I move to approve on second
reading.
>> Second. We have a motion from Councilman
Crrave, a second from Councilwoman Dr.
Emmens. Is there any discussion?
>> Councilman Labour.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
I believe earlier in our discussion
here, you mentioned that uh possibly my
questions for Skybox and VN West would
be appropriate under the uh this element
of our actions today. Is that
>> And I misspoke. It will be the next item
which is where we're talking about going
from agricultural to business park.
I see. Well, I'll wait for that. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with
recommendation to approve on second
reading. Next meeting of the council.
Our last and final item today. If you
would read that, please. Jennifer.
Number 12. I. Ordinance second reading.
Amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne. Changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road from AG Agricultural to BP Business
Park.
>> Okay. Staff report please.
>> Madam Chair, Connor White Planning and
Development Department.
So the zone change before you, it is
applicant requested. Um it is only for
the Cox Land Rox Ranch land. So 1,197.76
acres. Um the request is to go from the
AG agricultural zone to BP business
park.
Um so I said I was going to explain why
we kind of look at these separately. Uh
this goes back to with annexation.
Annexation does not define the use of
the land. So when we're looking at
annexation, we're looking at state
statute requirements for annexation.
Whatever the use is, that doesn't matter
at the time of annexation. Um we look at
that when it comes to the zoning. I
understand it is all one project. Um
it can it gets discussed all at once in
most cases,
but annexation doesn't define the use.
If this land isn't annexed, it can still
develop in the county. It could still
develop as a data center. Um so that's
why we don't look at the zone or we
don't look at the use with the
annexation. It's just is it going to be
under city jurisdiction or county
jurisdiction?
with the zone change. That's when we
dive into what is the use going to be,
what is the proposed use, what uses can
this zone district allow, um and does it
fit within the area.
So again, this is just for the Cox Ranch
land. This does not include the city's
own parcel. Uh the city's own parcel was
part of that last assigned zoning which
would basically keep it as Public.
Um so again with the zone change again
why we discuss them different or uh
separately is if the zone change isn't
approved but the land is annexed and
assigned the AG zone it sits as AG
agricultural which doesn't allow for
data centers. Um
the applicant has requested the BP as we
all know for a data center development.
Um the P the BP zone is adjacent to the
requested area. Um North Range Business
Park is zoned BP uh business park.
The BP zone is meant for larger parcels
and larger acreages. It does allow for a
mix of whether it be light industrial,
heavy industrial or community business
uh zoned uses.
Um
BP zone requires 320 acres.
This meets it on its own, but would also
meet it by being adjacent to the North
Range Business Park.
There is a future land use map amendment
that does go along with this. Um as I
mentioned at the beginning of the
meeting that is uh postponed another two
weeks for discussion. Uh the future land
use map is to mixeduse employment which
would support the uh business park zone
district. Um
so that is a lot of the background on
this one. Um I am available for any
questions.
>> Thank you. Is there any question for
staff?
Okay. Uh public comment
Mr.
U Madam Chair, uh Brad Emmens, AVI agent
for the owner and applicant. Uh this is
a request uh for the BP zone. Um I
believe when this council uh did approve
the BP zone um maybe a year ago at this
time. Um this is the type of property
that it was set up to meant to be. Um a
lot of the reason of for the BP zone
here is for the landscaping
requirements. Um there's reduced
landscaping
um in the BP compared to the LU LI or
the HI or the CB which all would also
allow for data centers. So um when um
the Northrange Business Park was brought
in um we looked at uh how it worked as a
PUD, how it looked, how all those things
and that helped derive the BP the BP
zone. So, uh, therefore, um, that's why
the team selected, um, BP for this area.
And, um, just wanted to, maybe there's a
little confusion on the BOP, but the
whole BOPU thing was to be on the same
map, same time through it. The they're
not combining the parcels. They're not
using each other. They're both can go
separately. Um, it was just so that it
could all be com combined on one map.
So, just wanted to clarif clarify that
one more time.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah,
>> Mr. Glistier, thank you for your
patience.
>> Of course. Thank you, committee.
>> We have just a few a few slides just as
it uh relates to the project. Uh I'd
like to again just reiterate that we
have a uh public open house on September
15th at 12:30 p.m. at the uh library in
the Cottonwood room. Um we've had great
turnout so far um members of the Rolling
Hills community. We've had um our
immediate neighbors uh right next door,
Mr. Eley, Mr. Gallotus. Um we've had
great conversations and have really
enjoyed getting to know them. Um so if
we could just quickly go through a few
of these um slides. This is this is the
a conceptual layout. Uh we're not
planning to build uh on
very much of the parcel. It was an all
ornone transaction. Uh our goal is to
keep uh near HappyJack where all of the
infrastructure is. Uh we're
about a quarter mile at the property
line to the nearest Rolling Hills uh
resident. We intend to build uh over a
half mile beyond that.
Uh I think there'll be lots of grazing
opportunities uh on the property. We'll
have to go through all of the typical
development steps, all of the
engineering to maintain water flows and
account for all of the existing
conditions uh including wetlands and
species environmental cultural studies.
So we we have a lot of a lot of work to
do um still ahead of us.
Uh this is uh just a just a snip from
the video just to underscore the
efficiency of the new modern facilities.
Um it's it's really the equivalent of
four to six homes uh worth of water. Uh
and that's primarily the restrooms and
the sinks for the employees. Um next
slide, please.
Uh this is a uh directly from Black
Hills. uh we've been coordinating with
them frequently and since the beginning
we pay 100% of our way. There will be no
cost passed on to the rateayers. That's
that's a requirement. It's been that way
for a long time and we uh we think
that's how it should be. U next slide
please.
Uh as I mentioned this uh upcoming
meeting will be our fifth uh and it will
not be our last. We intend to do it. Uh
it's how we uh how we operate. Uh
Councilman Labour, we've um Skybox has
developed around a dozen data centers uh
in many different communities and
operated them since 2012.
Um
we not only uh intend to be engaged in
uh community initiatives and be
responsive to what the community is
saying. We wish we could have a contract
with each and every member of the
community. It's I don't think it's
feasible. We're trying to gather uh
information uh and understand what's
important and try to do the best we can
to address those things in uh we're
we're calling it a a contract with the
community and trying to touch on all of
those uh all of those items that
everyone cares about. Um next next
slide, please.
uh this is an overview of that and some
of the things that we'll uh that that we
are going to address and and we have a
have a I think a great outline uh
drafted up uh things like jobs and
environment landscaping down to traffic
and water and light and noise during
construction after construction.
Um there's still dozens of reports that
that need to be done. It's as with any
development though. That's that's not
not unique to data center. There there's
a lot of lot of work to do once we know
we have a project. That's u that's
something that it it really isn't
feasible to do uh everything all at once
up front. Um I'll pause there and that's
uh I I'd happily answer any questions
that anyone might have. Thank you. Thank
you,
>> Councilman Labour. Did you have a
question?
>> Yes, I did. Thank you, Madam Chairman.
Um,
I'm interested to hear about the
corporate history of your uh
outfit.
So, since 2012 is quite a while. And did
you say 12 uh facilities that you
constructed
>> approximately? And and to be clear, I'm
I'm
I can I can speak completely to the
history of Vio Group. Um I've I've been
been with them for 11 or 12 years and
have been it's a it's a firm I'm very
proud to be associated with. has been uh
developer of the year many times um in
Arizona by the uh NAOP community which
is a commercial real estate development
community that is is a national
organization but um something like five
or six of the last 10 years been owner
developer of the year. Skybox um our our
partner has done uh nothing but own and
operate and develop data centers since
2012.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> that's Labour.
>> So my assumption is that with that
number of facilities and that
differences in location,
um there must be
a lot of factors that come into play.
But um in any of those cases, has your
uh corporation
committed to community benefits
at the very beginning of the process as
we're like we're at today. I mean it is
annexation. Um, so are the is that I
have no idea what they do in Arizona,
but I do know that uh there is a
certainly a lot of questions that public
is bringing forward about data centers
that u probably like a lot of us didn't
didn't anticipate this kind of activity.
So, um,
what what sort of, uh, community
commitments have you made over time,
>> Madam Chair? Three, Councilman, we, uh,
we I'm not aware of any process that has
unfolded quite like this one. Um it's
it's a it's a it we are in uncharted
waters um so to speak, but we're we're
we're happy to have this commitment to
the community
um framework and you know there I I I I
wish that we you know we're a a a p we
are privately owned companies um not not
backed um or owned by big private equity
firms. Um I I I don't we're we're doing
our best to commit as much as we can
before we know that we before we even
have a a viable operational project. I
think um as as time goes on, it's um if
you if you look at the track record and
the community engagement that Skybox has
done uh with their other projects, um
it's significant and it's it's
meaningful and it's ongoing.
Um, you know, we're we understand that
every every community is different and
every community has different um
different needs. We're not presuming to
come in and say you you it looks like
you need this. We're we we want to
understand what exactly that is at that
time. Um, but to make substantial
monetary commitments now before we um
before we even know whether we're
permitted to go forward is is very
difficult.
Madam Chairman,
>> uh, one more and then Councilman
Councilwoman Emmens has a question as
well. I want to make sure that she has
her a chance.
>> Sure.
>> Um, so in your commitment to the
community, your last bullet point here
is um, community contribution will
mutually agree upon a community
investment once operational.
Um,
am I correct that that's years down the
road? would be approximately
approximately two years from now if all
were to go well. Um that would that
would be the soonest we could be um
up and running
just with even the long long lead times
for equipment. Um and so and the
construction timeline, our our project
is is contemplated as being probably a
five to sevenyear project. um you know,
two to three buildings that um you know,
our our efforts would go into the into
all into the first one and then it would
roll into into the second or uh
potentially third. But that's
>> And who would you mutually agree with?
>> Councilman with the city.
>> Excuse me. with the city.
It is if it
if there is a a city project that um the
council has in mind that needs uh
attention, we're
happy to h have that discussion and
figure out a a way to
uh solve that issue.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilwoman Emmens. Thank
you, Madam Chairwoman. I have two
questions. One, and this is I think
where um Councilman Laburn was going. Um
I would anticipate, and please tell me
if I'm wrong, that at some point after
you get established, the mayor as the
city executive would potentially meet
with you to say, "We need help with
housing for your workforce." Is that
something that we could partner with?
Would that be the kind of scenario that
you're talking about?
>> Councilman, through you, Dr. Evans. Yes.
Something like that. Um, you know,
whether it's a um a commitment to a a
community project or a a park or uh what
whatever at the at the time there may be
a need for and we understand that those
change and and evolve over time, but
something like that. Yeah.
>> And then follow up, Madam Chair. Um,
then my second question is just to I
want to be crystal clear on this. What
what I've heard mentioned here is that
the company would pay for 100% of the
cost of necessary infrastructure to your
facility, whether that be sewage lines.
If for some reason the um Bo Pooh said
your
pipes aren't big enough um to meet the
need um if you need a separate road for
something you would pay 100% of that the
cost of that would not be borne by the
city. Is that correct?
>> Madam Chair through you Dr. Emmens
that's correct.
>> Any anything further Mr. Meire.
>> Uh, please come out to September 15th,
12:30 p.m.
>> Any other public comment?
>> And Jennifer, do you have the time?
>> We're still under public comment
>> and we are under
>> through you, Miss Madam Chairman.
Michael White.
Um,
I'd like to make a statement that was
given by Governor Gordon.
It's a monumental task to stretch to
thread the needle between unbridled
growth and regulations.
And to go further,
um, this project is
zoned under business park.
And to my knowledge, visit with Governor
Gordon's staff that under this
particular uh zoning and use
some of the regulations with state
government can be exempt.
We rely a lot on the industrial site
council to address the concerns that the
public has. Unfortunately,
our rules have not been updated for a
number of years. So I would make that
comment
that the one reason that we had this
discussion and was able to postpone some
of this was the discussion we had
earlier but also the discussions that
I'm aware of that the state executive
branch governor Gordon has asked staff
to make recommendations concerning these
particular sites and to my knowledge we
have not got to that point. In addition,
I believe that uh since I'm a taxpayer,
I understand what was just said about
what the skybox would pay for, but let's
take it one step further.
Legislators have allowed these
particular groups to come in and get a
tax break.
So my question is to Skybox
technically that means that I'm a
stakeholder. I'm a stockholder.
I should have even more
comments as a individual who is a land
owner
and basically able to tell these folks
that we need to have more information
because the taxpayers helping foot the
bill. We can talk about the power. We
can talk about everything else, but the
state legislators.
So, my final comment is that's where I'm
working at right now, state legislators
to help the public figure out what's
going on with these particular sites and
the zoning and what the state statutes
is. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi, Heather Madrid. uh ward one um to
his point about the industrial sighting
council I was at the def uh DEEQ
presentation and my understanding of
that is that what we're foregoing is
impact upfront impact payments but the
other part is the socioeconomic studies
that's not happening um by the DEEQ and
that's actually a big deal um
so okay so I'm going to stick to what I
was going to say um I oppose the zone
change because data centers have been
allowed to proliferate operate in our in
our backyards with no public oversight
once annexed into a business park. I
find it impossible to support any
project until there have been meaningful
changes to the UDC. These changes need
to start with defining data centers
appropriately to reflect what they
actually do and end use by right
permitting for them in business parks.
We need setbacks. We need a noise
ordinance that accounts for frequency,
vibration, and pitch rather than just
decibb. We need light pollution
ordinance. We need real consequences
when ordinances are repeatedly violated
instead of a slap on the wrist. We need
to regulate power generation, which by
the way will go before the planning
commission this evening where they will
introduce a vague amendment. I don't
think intentionally, but there's
loopholes that will propose power
generation of any kind become used by
right in business parks if they take
advantage of the loophole. Um, and they
will. Um, we need to address the housing
crisis that has been worsened by the
unchecked and frantic development on a
massive scale. Those are the kinds of
things that a socioeconomic impact study
would would help with is our our
housing, our hospital systems, our
school systems, etc. We're that's also
being missed by the bypass of the
industrial sighting council. Um, we need
to slow down. This council has been
saying since April that it is possible
to do two things at once, but nothing
has changed. In fact, things have only
escalated. Today, we're at the public
service committee meeting. This evening
we have the planning commission.
Tomorrow we have the Google open house
from 5:00 to 9:00 and the Traml Crow
openhouse from 7:00 to 8:30. If we want
a voice, I guess we need to find a a way
to be in two places at once. Next week
is the city council meeting on the 14th,
followed by another Skybox openhouse on
the 15th from 12:30 to 2. How do you
expect us to keep up at this pace? And
how are you keeping up at this pace? I
know you you know you have jobs. I have
a job. I had to take the day off because
I find it important to protect my
community from this and my kids and my
grandkids. Like this is it is
ridiculous.
Um
it's not and it's not sustainable. Maybe
I am a fool for believing that nobody's
pockets are being lined by any of this.
I think that people and their family and
friends maybe are privately benefiting
through businesses or whatever and maybe
why that's continuing to happen
unchecked. But my true belief is that at
this point it is about winning and it's
about power that some of you are maybe
afraid to admit this that this has
gotten way out of control and is no
longer able to be managed at this rate
in a responsible way. Maybe you don't
want to admit that a moratorum would
have allowed time to plan for what is
currently happening now. Maybe you don't
see a way out of this mess. And if
that's the case, I can tell you that the
safest way out from a legal legal
perspective is to stop approving
amendments to the land use map.
Regardless of the reason, I would ask
that you take an honest look at your
reasons and evaluate if you think you
are truly at this time representing and
protecting the citizens or if you're
protecting your own egos.
Is there any other public comment?
Is there anyone online?
Councilman Moody.
>> Yes. Thank you, uh, Madame Chair. Mark
Woody, Shine City Council worker.
I won't repeat anything, but just what
was said by two of the, uh, two of our
constituents there.
right on point. You know that that's a
lot here. I really do think we need to
slow down. Nothing is in writing about a
community benefit. It needs to be in
writing if there's actually going to
commit to that. So all site. Thank you.
>> Any other public comment online?
Hearing none and seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
Madame Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilwoman Dr.
Evans and a second from Councilman
Crave. Is there any discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve on second
reading at the next meeting of the
council. We've concluded our business on
the agenda for today. Thank you and have
a great day.